Guide to the James Laurence Laughlin Papers 1885-1914
University of Chicago Library
Laughlin, James Laurence. Papers
1885-1914
.5 linear ft. ( 1 box)
Hanna Holborn Gray Special Collections Research Center University of Chicago Library 1100 East 57th Street Chicago, Illinois 60637 U.S.A.
J. Laurence Laughlin (1850-933), Professor of Political Economy, editor of the Journal of Political Economy. The J. Laurence Laughlin Papers consist of a small collection of writings, correspondence, lectures notes and miscellany. The primary focus of the collection centers on two economic controversies in which Laughlin was involved concerning U. S. silver monetary policy and the legality and benefits of labor unions.
Information on Use
Access
No restrictions.
Biographical Note
James Laurence Laughlin was born on April 2, 1850 in Deerfield, Ohio. In the fall of 1869 he entered Harvard College and was graduated summa cum laude in history in 1873. He continued the study of history under Henry Adams at Harvard. He also taught at Hopkinson's Classical School in Boston. In 1876 he received his Ph. D. degree for his thesis on "The Anglo-Saxon Legal Procedure."
In the fall of 1878 Laughlin was appointed instructor of political economy at Harvard. After receiving graduate training in economics, he was appointed an assistant professor at Harvard (1883-1888); during this period, Laughlin organized and sponsored the Political Economy Club. He also completed his History of Bimetallism in the United States in 1885. In 1888 Laughlin left Harvard and became president of the Manufacturer's Mutual Life Insurance Company of Philadelphia. He accepted a professorship in Political Economy at Cornell University in 1890.
Two years later President Harper appointed Laughlin Head Professor of Political Economy at the new University of Chicago. At Chicago, Laughlin introduced the seminar as a method of instruction and founded the Journal of Political Economy. In 1894, Laughlin proposed that the University establish a School of Commerce and Industry. The new professional school, which began undergraduate instruction in 1898, evolved into the Graduate School of Business.
In 1916 Laughlin became Professor Emeritus. He moved to East Jaffery, New Hampshire, where he completed his Credit of Nations, published in 1918. He also wrote numerous magazine articles, largely on labor questions, including "Monopoly of Labor." He died on November 28, 1933.
Scope Note
The J. Laurence Laughlin Papers consist of a small collection of writings, correspondence, lectures notes and miscellany. The primary focus of the collection centers on two economic controversies in which Laughlin was involved concerning U. S. silver monetary policy and the legality and benefits of labor unions.
Related Resources
Browse finding aids by topic.
Subject Headings
Laughlin, J. Laurence (James Laurence), 1850-1933; Monetary policy; Labor unions; Silver question; Economists
INVENTORY
- Correspondence 1885-1898, J. B. Aldrich N. (?) B. Anderson C. Schurz James F. Colby S. Newcomb Henry E. Sawyer H. H. Kohlsaat C. A. Woods to H. H. Kohlsaat H. H. Kohlsaat H. W. Hawley William S. Poppleton to H.H. Kohlsaat Edw. A. Temple Horace White Stuart C. Wade Stuart C. Wade Edward Ericson Eugene F. Baldwin L. F. Houghton Rozel Weissinger J. M. Hagar H. W. Van Sendry (?) Wm. H. Fitch J. T. Beem E. A. Congdon C. McAuliff M. Fell, Jr. Thomas F. Byron Clark Conkling Edw. S. Elliott D. A. Orebaugh to Editor [of the Time Herald] to be passed on to Laughlin W[illiam] J. Fischer John Serrigan Bell R.E. Preston(?) (Director of the Mint, 1895) "S.T." to H.H. Kohlsaat Richard W. Knott Horace Rublee A.D. Noyes (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Correspondence 1903-1914, Mathias von Holst to Carl Marr Carl Marr to Mathias von Holst Carl Marr Carl Marr E.E. Prussing Laughlin to John A. Cook A. M. Wergeland Nicholas Murrary Butler Laughlin to F. Burdick Laughlin to Ellery Sedgewick Albert Farwell Bemis Laughlin to Albert F. Bemis Laughlin to H.L. Gregory A.C. Dutton Laughlin to Ellery Sedgewick Laughlin to A.C. Dutton Laughlin to Ellery Sedgewick Laughlin to Jerome D. Greene Laughlin to C. B. Spencer Arthur T. Lyman Laughlin to Arthur T. Lyman A. C. Kingsford Laughlin A.C. Kingsford W.R. Ingalls Laughlin to W. R. Ingalls Laughlin to Rev. John O. Grady (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Manuscript, "Monopoly of Labor"-holograph draft (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Manuscript, "Monopoly of Labor"-holograph draft and typescript draft (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Manuscript, "Monopoly of Labor"-holograph draft and outline (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Manuscript, Credit of the Nations [1918]-Preface (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Manuscript, Credit of the Nations [1918]-Chapter I (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Manuscript, Credit of the Nations [1918]-Chapter II (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Manuscript, Credit of the Nations [1918]-Chapter III (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Manuscript, Credit of the Nations [1918]-Chapter IV (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Manuscript, Credit of the Nations [1918]-Chapter V (Box 1, Folder 11)
- Manuscript, Credit of the Nations [1918]-Chapter VI (Box 1, Folder 12)
- Manuscript, Credit of the Nations [1918]-Appendix I (Box 1, Folder 13)
- Manuscript, Credit of the Nations [1918]-Miscellaneous drafts (Box 1, Folder 14)
- Lecture notes from Samuel Eliot's course Nineteenth Century taken by J. Laurence Laughlin (Box 1, Folder 15)
- Instructors grade book: "Railways, 1891-1892" (Box 1, Folder 16)
- Miscellaneous texts, "Fifty Books on Bimetallism, Free Coinage of Silver, Paper-Mondy, and Banking. Selected and Described by Prof. J. Laurence Laughlin," pamphlet, after 1895 "Our Currency: What are its Defects?... A Discussion before the Commercial Club of Chicago," October 27, 1894 "The Sunset Club, Chicago," proceedings, December 6, 1894 "Professor Laughlin to the Doctors of Philosophy," address to the Association of Doctors of Philosophy, June 6, 1916 Scheme for the Department of Political Economy and Finance in Cornell University, Presented to the Board of Trustees," March 2, 1891 "Is the Gold Law a Failure?" The Economist, July 14, 1900 (Box 1, Folder 17)
- "To the President and Trustees of the University of Chicago," draft of open letter from faculty in the Social Sciences requesting additional University support, circa 1907 (Box 1, Folder 18)